MUHAMMAD RASHED

2550 N Alafaya Trl, Apt. 10305, Orlando, Florida, 32826 muhammad.rashed@ucf.edu +1(210)-910-7104 +1(210)-910-7104 Website: https://mrhrashed.github.io/

SUMMARY

I am a PhD candidate in Computer Engineering at the University of Central Florida (UCF). My expected graduation date is Spring 2024 and I am on the academic job market for tenure-track assistant professor positions starting Fall 2024. My research interests include EDA for emerging computing paradigms and architectures, computer-aided design, and, artificial intelligence. On these topics, I have published 18 top-tier journals and conference papers. I have a total of 10 publications on the prestigious CSRanking list. My ICCAD paper in 2022 was nominated for the IEEE/ACM William J. McCalla ICCAD Best Paper Award and, my DAC paper in 2022 was recognized as a Publicity Paper at the conference.

EDUCATION

University of Central Florida, Orlando

January 2020 - present

PhD in Computer Engineering, Department of ECE

(Expected in Spring 2024)

Thesis: Towards Energy-Efficient In-Memory Computing Systems using Design Automation

Supervisor: Prof. Rickard Ewetz

University of Texas at San Antonio, San Antonio

August 2018 - December 2019

Graduate Coursework, Department of ECE

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology

May 2010- September 2015

Bachelor of Science, Department of Electrical and Electronics Engineering

AWARDS AND HONORS

• IEEE/ACM William J. McCalla ICCAD Best Paper Award Nomination	2022
• Best Research Video Award at the Design Automation Conference (DAC)	2021
\bullet Acknowledgment of the XORG Paper as a Publicity Paper at \mathbf{DAC}	2022
• David T. and Jane M. Donaldson Memorial Graduate Scholarship	2022
\bullet IEEE/ACM DATE PhD Forum Best Doctoral Dissertation Competition Finalist	2023
\bullet IEEE/ACM DAC PhD Forum Best Doctoral Dissertation Competition Finalist	2022
• NSF Travel Grant (2021–2024), DATE Travel Grant (2023), UCF SGA Travel Grant (2023–ACM Travel Grant (2022)	2024),
• The Presentation Fellowship by UCF Graduate Studies	$2021\!-\!2023$
• 3MT Research Finalist at the University of Texas at San Antonio	2019
• Education Board Scholarship for HSC, SSC and JSC result	2005 - 2015

RESEARCH PAPER PUBLICATIONS

Major Research Topics:

- Electronic Design Automation (EDA) for Emerging Computing Paradigms
- Artificial Intelligence (AI) and Machine Learning (ML)
- Computer-aided Design (CAD) for Very Large-Scale Integration (VLSI)
- Computer Architecture

Peer-Reviewed Publications:

[P22] [DAC'24] M Rashed, S Thijssen, D. Simon, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Execution Sequence Optimization for Processing In-Memory using Parallel Data Preparation", in 61st Design Automation Conference (DAC), 2024. [CSRanking]

- [P21] [DAC'24] S Thijssen, M Rashed, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Synthesis of Compact Flow-based Computing Circuits from Boolean Expressions", in 61st Design Automation Conference (DAC), 2024. [CSRanking]
- [P20] [ASP-DAC'24] S Thijssen, M Rashed, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "READ-based In-Memory Computing using Sentential Decision Diagrams", 29th Asia and South Pacific Design Automation Conference (ASP-DAC), 2024. (accepted)
- [P19] [ASP-DAC'24] S Thijssen, M Rashed, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Towards Area-Efficient Path-Based In-Memory Computing using Graph Isomorphisms", 29th Asia and South Pacific Design Automation Conference (ASP-DAC), 2024. (accepted)
- [P18] [ICCAD'23] M Rashed, S Thijssen, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Automated Synthesis for In-Memory Computing", 42nd International Conference On Computer Aided Design (ICCAD), 2023. [CSRanking]
- [P17] [ICCAD'23] M Rashed, S Thijssen, SK Jha, H Zheng, and R Ewetz, "Path-based Processing using In-Memory Systolic Arrays for Accelerating Data-Intensive Applications", 42nd International Conference On Computer Aided Design (ICCAD), 2023. [CSRanking]
- [P16] [ICCAD'23] S Thijssen, S. Singireddy, <u>M Rashed</u>, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Verification of Flow-Based Computing Systems using Bounded Model Checking", 42nd International Conference On Computer Aided Design (ICCAD), 2023. [CSRanking]
- [P15] [TCAD'23] M Rashed, S Thijssen, F Yao, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "STREAM: Towards READ-based In-Memory Computing for Streaming Based Processing for Data-Intensive Applications", IEEE Transactions on Computer-Aided Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems (TCAD), 2023
- [P14] [TCAD'23] S Thijssen, M Rashed, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "PATH: Evaluation of Boolean Logic using Path-based In-Memory Computing Systems", IEEE Transactions on Computer-Aided Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems (TCAD), 2023.
- [P13] [ICCD'23] S. Singireddy, <u>M Rashed</u>, S Thijssen, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Input-Aware Flow-Based In-Memory Computing", 41st International Conference on Computer Design (ICCD), 2023.
- [P12] [DAC'23] S Thijssen, M Rashed, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "UpTime: Towards Flow-based In-Memory Computing with High Fault-Tolerance", in 60th Design Automation Conference (DAC), 2023. [CSRanking]
- [P11] [ASP-DAC'23] M Rashed, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Discovering the In-Memory Kernels of 3D Dot-Product Engines", 28th Asia and South Pacific Design Automation Conference (ASP-DAC), 2023.
- [P10] [ICCAD'22] M Rashed, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Logic Synthesis for Digital In-Memory Computing", 41st International Conference On Computer Aided Design (ICCAD), 2022. (Best paper nomination) [CSRanking]
- [P9] [DAC'22] M Rashed, A Awad, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Towards Resilient Analog In-Memory Deep Learning via Data Layout Re-Organization", 59th Design Automation Conference (DAC), 2022. (Publicity Paper) [CSRanking]
- [P8] [DATE'22] M Rashed, SK Jha, F Yao and R Ewetz, "Hybrid Digital-Digital In-Memory Computing", 25th Design Automation and Test in Europe Conference (DATE), 2022.
- [P7] [ASP-DAC'22] M Rashed, S Thijssen, F Yao, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "STREAM: Towards READ-based In-Memory Computing for Streaming based Data Processing", 27th Asia and South Pacific Design Automation Conference (ASP-DAC), 2022.
- [P6] [ICCAD'21] M Rashed, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Hybrid Analog-Digital In-Memory Computing", 40th International Conference On Computer Aided Design (ICCAD), 2021. [CSRanking]
- [P5] [MICRO'21] M Chowdhuryy, M Rashed, A Awad, R Ewetz, and F Yao, "LADDER: Architecting Content and Location-aware Writes for Crossbar Resistive Memories", 54th International Symposium on Microarchitecture (MICRO), 2021. [CSRanking]

 Prior to PhD:
- [P4] [ICAEE'17] M Rashed, M Zaman, M Islam and M Raihan, "An analysis on the required reinforcement for embedding a nuclear power plant in a generic power system", 4th International Conference on Advances in Electrical Engineering (ICAEE), 2017.

- [P3] [EICT'17] S Saha, S Ukil and M Rashed, "Numerical investigation on the performance of new ultra-thin CZTS solar cell using SCAPS", 3rd International Conference on Electrical Information and Communication Technology (EICT), 2017.
- [P2] [ICAEE'17] A Dewanjee, N Dey, <u>M Rashed</u>, A Muhury and J Dhar, "High performance cost effective formalin detector using conductivity property", 4th International Conference on Advances in Electrical Engineering (ICAEE), 2017.
- [P1] [ICECE'16] M Nadim, M Rashed, A Muhury and S Mominuzzaman, "Estimation of optimum tilt angle for PV cell: A study in perspective of Bangladesh", 9th International Conference on Electrical and Computer Engineering (ICECE), 2016.

Under Review/Submission Publications:

- [U4] [TCAD'23] M Rashed, S Thijssen, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "LOGIC: Logic Synthesis for Digital In-Memory Computing", IEEE Transactions on Computer-Aided Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems (TCAD), 2023. (under review).
- [U3] S Thijssen, <u>M Rashed</u>, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Efficient Runtime Management of Crossbars for Path-based In-Memory Computing". (under submission)
- [U2] S Thijssen, M Rashed, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Efficient Runtime Management of Crossbars for Path-based In-Memory Computing". (under submission)
- [U1] H. Chugh, <u>M Rashed</u>, F. Yao, and R Ewetz, "Side Channel Attack in ReRAM Crossbar". (under submission)

TALKS/POSTER PRESENTATIONS

[T3] [DATE'22] PhD Forum, in 26th Design Automation and Test in Europe Conference (DATE)	2023
[T2] [DAC'22] PhD Forum, in 59th Design Automation Conference (DAC)	2022
[T1] [DAC'21] Young Fellow Program, in 58th Design Automation Conference (DAC)	2021

GRANT PROPOSAL WRITING EXPERIENCE

I have assisted my supervisor Prof. Rickard Ewetz with 7 grant proposal submissions on EDA and AI to the National Science Foundation (NSF), Department of Energy (DOE), and, Cyber-Florida. To date, the proposals have been awarded a total grant of \$825,000.

Selected Proposals:

- Collaborative Research: FMitF: Track I: Synthesis and Verification of In-Memory Computing Systems using Formal Methods. (Awarded \$750,000).
- Security-Aware In-Memory Neural Networks for Cyber-Physical Systems (Awarded \$75,000).
- An Analysis of Semiconductor Workforce Development using National Science Foundation Support at Hispanic Serving Institutions in the United States.
- Collaborative Research: Elements: Cyberinfrastructure for End-to-End Design, Synthesis, and Validation of In-Memory Computing Systems.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

University of Central Florida

January 2020 - present

Graduate Research Assistant

- Developed a logic synthesis framework for digital in-memory computing. The framework improves the area-latency of multiplication operations by 77% and 20% over the state-of-the-art. [P10], [P17]
- Designed an in-memory systolic array system using path-based in-memory computing. The system is 23X faster than traditional systolic arrays. [P16]
- Developed an efficient 3D dot product engine (DPE) architecture that achieves 2.02X, 2.37X, and 2.45X improvements in area, energy, and latency respectively over 2D DPE. [P11]
- Developed a data layout re-organization framework for analog in-memory deep learning. The framework improves precision in hardware by up to 3.2X. [P9]

- Developed design automation infrastructure for hybrid analog-digital in-memory computing. The hybrid paradigm achieved 2.5X overhead improvement over state-of-the-art paradigms. [P6], [P8]
- Proposed a streaming-based in-memory computing architecture for evaluating Boolean logic. The architecture improves performance over state-of-the-art by up to 20X by eliminating expensive and error-prone WRITE operations. [P13], [P7]
- Delivered an effective and low-cost location and data-aware processor-side architecture for memristor-based memory systems. The framework called LADDER achieves 13.2% performance improvement over state-ofthe-art designs. [P5]

University of Texas at San Antonio

August 2018-December 2019

Graduate Research Assistant

• Developed secure automated vehicular communication protocol between OBU and RSU units.

Abul Khair Steel Melting Limited

October 2015-June 2018

Technical Management

- Supervised electrical power distribution in the Main Receiving Substation (MRSS).
- Supervised the routine electrical maintenance to circumvent breakdowns. Reduced equipment shut-down by two occurrences per year.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

- C++ and Data Structures (UTSA)
 - Object-oriented programming including data abstraction, inheritance, operator overloading, and polymorphism. Application of OOP to study various data structures including stacks, queues, linked lists, trees, binary trees, and graphs.
- \bullet Engineering Analysis and Computation (UCF)
 - Engineering analysis and computation with structured constructs. Subscripted variables, functions, input/output. Applications in embedded systems and examples in numerical methods.
- Guest Lecture/ Course Development: Computer-Aided Design of VLSI (UCF)
 An introduction to computer-aided design (CAD) for very large scale integration (VLSI). The focus is on algorithms and data structures that are used within logic synthesis.

MENTORING EXPERIENCE

I have mentored 9 graduate students + 7 undergraduate students + 9 high-school (10-12 grades) students + 1 industry affiliate. (Diversity: 6 female advisees, 2 black students, 2 Hispanic students, 1 first-gen college student, and, 1 student with a learning disability)

Selected Advisees

- Sven Thijssen, Ph.D. student @UCF, Achievements: [P21], [P20], [P19], [P16], [P14], [P12], [U2-U4]
- Hardik Chugh, MS student @UCF, Achievements: [U1]
- Stacey Alexander, industry affiliate @UTSA
- Suraj Singireddy, Ph.D. student @UTSA, Achievements: [P13]

• Technical Reviewer, International Conference on Computer Design (ICCD)

• Austin Ramos, undergraduate student @UTSA

PROFESSIONAL SERVICE

• Session Chair, Design Automation Conference (DAC)	2022
• Technical Reviewer, IEEE Internet of Things Journal	2023
\bullet Technical Reviewer, IEEE Transactions on Emerging Topics in Computing	2022
\bullet Technical Reviewer, International Symposium on Quality Electronic Design (ISQED)	2024

2021, 2022

• Technical Reviewer, The Great Lakes Symposium on VLSI (GLSVLSI)	2021, 2022
• Technical Reviewer, International Conference on AI Circuits and Systems (AICAS)	2022, 2023

COMMUNITY SERVICE AND EXTRACURRICULAR ACTIVITY

• Guiding prospective international students with graduate school application process	2018-present
\bullet Supporting incoming international students at UCF with housing & transportation	2020-present
• Served as the Vice President of the Bangladesh Student Association (BSA) at UTSA	2018 - 2019

SKILLS

- \bullet $Programming\ Language:$ C++, Python, MATLAB and Verilog.
- EDA Tools: Design Compiler, ABC, YOSYS, SIS, Vivado Design Suite, CACTI 7, ARM Forge
- Operating Systems and Software: Linux, Windows, Office Software, Latex, AutoCad.

TRAINING

• Responsible Conduct of Research for Engineers- Stage 2 (CITI)	2023
• Authorship, Credit and Collaborative Scholarship (UCF)	2022
• Doing the Right Thing: Know About Research Misconduct (UCF)	2022
\bullet at-risk for University and College Faculty and Stuff (UCF)	2020
• at-risk Friends in College (UCF)	2020
• Employee Code of Conduct & Speak Up Whistleblower Training (UCF)	2020
• Academic Integrity Module (UCF)	2020
• Responsible Conduct of Research for Engineers- Stage 1 (CITI)	2020
• Teaching Assistant Training (UTSA)	2019